Francesco Scala

REASEARCH FELLOW IN OUANTUM MACHINE LEARNING

Pavia, Italy

■ francesco.scala01@ateneopv.it | ★ Personal page: fran-scala.github.io/ | ☑ fran-scala | Ⅲ fran-scala



Summary _

I'm an eager **researcher** in **Quantum Machine Learning** (QML) at University of Pavia, focusing on both classical and quantum machine learning. I bring **strong foundations** in state-of-the-art **theoretical aspects of QML** as well as **proficiency in numerical simulations** of quantum computing systems and QML algorithms.

Work Experience _____

FULL-TIME

Oct - Dec 2024 Research fellow University of Pavia

Pavia - Italy

Research fellowship focused on overparametrization in Quantum Machine Learning in collaboration with the research group led by **Dario Gerace**.

2021 - 2024

PhD in Quantum Machine Learning University of Pavia

Pavia - Italy

My research dealt with **QML algorithms**, with special focus on **overparametrization** and **regularization** properties of **Quantum Neural Networks**. Part of my studies are also devoted to simulations of controlling **integrated quantum photonics**. Supervisor: Prof. **Dario Gerace**.

Mar - May 2024

Visiting PhD IBM RESEARCH

Zurich - Switzerland

Research internship focused on Quantum Machine Learning. Supervisors: Dr. Ivano Tavernelli, Dr. Francesco Tacchino. and Dr. Christa Zoufal.

PART-TIME

2022-24 **Teaching assistant** University of Pavia

Pavia - Italy

- General Physics: preparation for the exam at the degree program in Chemistry and Pharmaceutical Technologies (2022-24)
- Computational methods (bash, C++): preparation for the exam at the degree program in Physics (2023-24)

Jul - Dec 2022

Intern QUANTUM COMPUTING LAB - CINECA

Casalecchio di Reno (BO) - Italy

Benchmarking of **HPC infrastructures** for quantum computing and **QML applications** (Python). Supervisor: Dr. **Riccardo Mengoni**

Education

2019 - 2021 Master degree in Physics of Quantum Technologies University of Pavia

Pavia - Italy

Graduation date: 23-09-2021, Thesis: "Witnessing Entanglement by Quantum Neural Networks".

2016 - 2019

Bachelor degree in Physics University of Pavia

Pavia - Italy

Graduation date: 24-09-2019, Thesis: "Machine learning techniques applied to the quantum many-body problem".

Contributions: conferences, schools _____

Nov 2023 Quantum Techniques in Machine Learning (QTML) 2023 CERN

Geneve - Switzerland

Talk: A General Approach to Dropout in Quantum Neural Networks

Oct 2023 Quantum Computing and Simulation Workshop ISTITUTO VENETO

Venezia - Italy

Poster: A General Approach to Dropout in Quantum Neural Networks

Aug 2023 Superconducting Qubits and Algorithms (SQA) Conference IQM QUANTUM COMPUTERS

Munich - Germany

Poster: Symmetrizing Quantum Machine Learning for Quantum Field Theory

International Conference on Optics of Excitons in Confined Systems Università del Salento Jun 2023 Lecce - Italy **Talk**: Quantum computing platform with polariton integrated circuits Quantum Techniques in Machine Learning (QTML) 2022 UNIVERSITY FEDERICO II Nov 2022 Napoli - Italy Poster: Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing VCQ & AppQlinfo SummerSchool 2022 UNIVERSITÄT WIEN Ago - Sept 2022 Wien - Austria Student Talk: Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing World Congress On Computational Intelligence 2022 IEEE Padova - Italy Talk: Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing Quantum Computing Hard- and Software Summer School 2022 EPFL, ETH ZÜRICH Lausanne - Switzerland **Poster**: Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing Extracurricular Activities _____ 2021-present Reviewer Journals-Conferences Online · Reviewer for Scientific Journals: Quantum Science and Technology, Quantum Machine Intelligence, Quantum Information Processing, International Journal of Theoretical Physics Reviewer for Scientific Conferences: Quantum Techniques in Machine Learning (QTML), IEEE Quantum Week Winner QUANTUM HACKATHONS 2022-present Online/In-presence • 2nd Place - QHack 2024 (Xanadu): Spectral Gap estimation [paper] [Github] • 1st Place - ETH Quantum Hackathon 2023 (IQM Challenge): Exploiting symmetries in Quantum Machine Learning [Github] • 2nd Place - MIT iQuHACK 2022 (Micrsoft/IonQ division): Quantum game with educational purposes [Github] Technical-scientific Committee Member BeQUANTUM Apr 2023 - present Online - Italy · Production of technical posts. General posts review. Apr 2022 - Jul 2022 Mentee Quantum Open Source Foundation (QOSF) Online Implementation of Krylov module within tequila Python package [Github] • Mentor: Prof. Jakob Kottmann Phd Student representative Università degli Studi di Pavia 2022 - 2023 Pavia - Italy Skills · Programming: Python, familiarity with C++, familiarity with high-performance computing (MPI, OpenMP) • Quantum programming: Pennylane (in combination with JAX), Qiskit, tequila, AWS Braket • Mark-up: LTFX, familiarity with html, CSS · Soft skills: predisposition to interpersonal relationships, teamwork, quick learner, proactive, time management Languages _____ Italian: Native English: Level C1 French: Level A1 Publications • F. Scala et al., In preparation, Quantum Neural Networks Diagnostics with Neural Tangent Kernels 2024 • F. Ghisoni, F. Scala et al., arXiv:2409.08929, Shadow Quantum Linear Solver 2024 • J. Kottmann, F. Scala, JCTC 20 (9), 3514-3523, Quantum Algorithmic Approach to Multiconfigurational Valence Bond Theory 2024 • F. Scala et al., Commun Phys 7, 118, Deterministic entangling gates with nonlinear quantum photonic interferometers 2024 • F. Scala et al. arXiv:2402.17668, Spectral Gap Superposition States 2024 • F. Scala et al., Adv. Quantum Technol. 2300220, A General Approach to Dropout in Quantum Neural Networks 2023 • F. Scala et al., IEEE - IJCNN 2022 Proceedings, Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing 2022